[Music]
Martin Luther King Jr warned that human
progress is neither automatic nor
inevitable and the same may be true of
the human lifespan in the 1800s life
expectancy was less than 40 but has been
steadily increasing over the last two
centuries gaining about two years per
decade that is until recently longevity
gains have faltered or even reversed
thanks to the Obesity epidemic we may
now be raising the first American
generation to live shorter lives than
their parents the downward Trend in
longevity is expected to accelerate as
the current younger generation who
started out heavier and earlier than
ever before ages into adulthood if the
Obesity epidemic Contin unchecked
current trends signal a potential
looming social and economic catastrophe
in the coming decades some predict we
may lose uh two to five or more years of
life expectancy in the United States I
mean to put that into perspective a
miracle cure for all forms of cancer
would only add 3.5 years to the average
American lifespan in other words
reversing the Obesity epidemic might
save more lives than curing cancer the
evidence being overweight increases your
risk for debilitating diseases like
diabetes is considered indisputable but
surprisingly there's controversy
surrounding body weight and overall
mortality in 2013 a CDC scientist
published a metanalysis and the Journal
of the American Medical Association
suggesting being overweight was actually
advantageous yes grade two or three
obesity like being average height 5'6
and weighing about 215 plus pounds was a
associated with living a shorter life
but grade one obesity between about 185
to 215 pounds at that height was not and
just being overweight 155 to 185 lbs
appeared to be protective compared to
those who were normal weight 115 to
155 the overweight individuals uh BMI 25
to 30 appeared to live the longest
headline writers were giddy right being
overweight can extend your life dreading
your diet don't worry plump people live
longer extra pounds might mean lower
chance of death not surprisingly the
study ignited a firestorm of controversy
in the Public Health Community the study
was called ludicrous flawed misleading
that share of nutrition at Harvard lost
his cool calling the study really a pile
of rubbish uh fearing the food industry
might exploit this study in the same way
the petroleum industry misuses
controversy over climate change Public
Health Advocates can't just dismiss data
they find inconvenient though I mean
science is science but how could being
overweight increase the risk of
life-threatening diseases yet at the
same time make you live longer this
became known as the Obesity Paradox the
solution to the puzzle appears to lie
with two major sources of bias the first
being confounding by smoking right the
nicotine and tobacco can lead to weight
loss so if you're skinnier because you
smoke well then no wonder you'd live a
shorter life with a Slimmer waste the
failure to control for the effect of
smoking in studies purporting to show an
obesity Paradox uh leads to the dangers
of obesity being grossly
underestimated the second major source
of bias is reverse causality instead of
lower weight leading to lifethreatening
diseases is it more likely that
life-threatening diseases are leading to
lower weight I conditions such as hidden
tumors chronic heart and lung disease
alcoholism and depression can all cause
unintentional weight loss months or even
years before they're even diagnosed it's
normal to be overweight in this country
right so people who are who are
abnormally thin in other words ideal
weight I mean could actually be taking
care of themselves right but maybe heavy
smokers elderly and frail or seriously
ill with weight loss from their
disease to put the Obesity hardock
issued to the test once and for all the
global BMI mortality collaboration was
formed reviewing data for more than 10
million people from hundreds of studies
in dozens of countries the largest
evaluation of BMI mortality in history
to help eliminate bias they omitted
smokers and those with known chronic
disease and then excluded the first five
years of follow-up to try to remove from
the analysis those with undiagnosed
conditions who lost weight due to an
impending death and the results were
clear being overweight and all grades of
obesity were associated with a
significantly greater risk of dying
prematurely so adjusting for these
biases leads to eliminating the Obesity
Paradox altogether in other words the
so-called obesity Paradox appears to be
just a myth indeed when intentional
weight loss is actually put to the test
people live longer they're iatric
surgery studies like the SOS trial that
show weight loss reduces long-term
mortality and randomizing people to
weight loss through Lifestyle Changes
shows the same thing losing a dozen
pounds through diet and exercise was
found to be associated with a 15% drop
in overall mortality now I mean exercise
alone may extend the lifespan even
without weight loss but there also
appears to be a similar longevity
benefit of weight loss through dietary
means
alone